Guide to the Norris Ingersoll Crandall papers, 1935-1954 MS2295.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Norris Ingersoll Crandall papers
1935-1954
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Crandall, Norris Ingersoll
MS2295.UA
3 Linear Feet
This collection contains material relating to the works and academic career of Norris I Crandall. Included are manuscript drafts, lecture notes, research notes and students papers dating from 1935-1954.
Biographical / Historical
Norris Ingersoll Crandall (1891-1973), a Professor Emeritus of Art and Architecture at George Washington University from 1923-1957. He was the head of the Department of Architecture from 1923-1927 and designer of Samson Hall.
Norris Crandall attained his Bachelors degree in Architecture from Cornell University in 1914 and his Master in Architecture in 1915, also from Cornell University.
Arrangement
Organized into 2 series: Manuscripts material and George Washington University material.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Thomas O'Callaghan, 2011 (Accession 2011.034)
Scope and Contents
Materials in this collection include research notes, manuscript drafts, correspondence, lecture notes and assignments and student writings The materials range in date from between 1935 and 1954.
Separated Materials
The following books were annotated by Dr. Crandall. These books are in the special collections book collection:
The essentials of composition as applied to art by John Vredenburgh Van Pelt, 1913
Expressionism in art by Sheldon Cheney, 1934
The arts and their interrelations by Thomas Munro, 1949
The things we see - no. 4 Pottery and glass by Bernard Hollowood, 1947
Art as experience by John Dewey, 1934
A history of esthetics by Katharine Everett Gilbert, 1939
Principles of art appreciation by Stephen C. Pepper, 1949
AND
The following books were donated, but not retained in the collection due to duplication or lack of research significance for the circulating collection.
History of art criticism by Lionello Venturi, 1936
A text-book of the history of architecture by A.D.F. Hamlin, 1909
Design and composition in line, form, and mass by Frederick J. Glass, 1925
A history of philosophy by B.A.G. Fuller, 1938
A history of architecture on the comparative method by Sir Banister Fletcher, 1921
The American Vignola part I by William R. Ware, 1905
The American Vignola part II by William R. Ware, 1925
Artists on art from XIV to the XX century, 1945
World of art by Eugen Neuhaus, 1936
Modern art in the making by Bernard S. Myers, 1950
Figure construction a brief treatise on drawing the human figure by Alon Bement, 1921
Styles in painting a comparative study by Paul Zucker, 1950
Art -- Study and teaching -- Washington (D.C.); George Washington University -- Students; Architecture
- Manuscripts material, 1940-1954; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically then chronologically
  Scope and Contents
  This series containes manuscript drafts written by Norris Crandall. Included are edits and hand drawn illustrations.
  - Art As I See it - early draft, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art As I See It - edited draft [1 of 2], 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art As I See It - edited draft [2 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Art As I See It - edited draft, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Art As I See It - draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Art As I See It - bound draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Art As I See It - bound draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Art As You See It - bound draft (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Art As You See It - a glossary, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Art As You See It - The Physical Elements in Visual Perception, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Art As You See It - Part I, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Art As You See It - illustrations, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Art As You See It - an introduction and two chapters (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Art As You See It - bound draft, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Art As I You See It - bound draft, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Artistic Backgrounds for Art Appreciation, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Artistic Backgrounds for Art Appreciation - research, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Historic Backgrounds for Art Appreciation, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Historic Backgrounds for Art Appreciation, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - History of Art Criticism outline, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Modern Art is a Habit, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The Color Cycle, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - The Perfect Home - the senses, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Questions on the Cubist Painters by Guillaume Apollinaire, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Theory of Analysis of Lightvalue and Color, 1947; 2 Linear Feet (Box 4, Folder 10)
- George Washington University material, 1935-1951; Series 2
  Arranged chronologically
  This series containes material relating to Norris Crandalls work at George Washington University dating from 1935-1951. Included are research and lecture notes, correspondence and works by students within Crandalls classes.
  - Work of Art Analysis Data, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Research notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Lecture topics and notes - bound, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Works by students, 1935-1949 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Works by students [1 of 2], 1950 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Works by students [2 of 2], 1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Works by students - art criticism [1 of 2], 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Works by students - art criticism [2 of 2], 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1937 (Box 6, Folder 1)